<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The indecency and unlawfulness of baptizing children in private, without necessity, and with the publick form seriously recommended to the consideration of both the clergy and laity of the Church of England : to which is added, a brief exhortation to the constant receiving of the Lords Supper.</title>
            <author>Strong, Martin, b. 1663 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61842</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5995</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15237</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13144590</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13144590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61842)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 780:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The indecency and unlawfulness of baptizing children in private, without necessity, and with the publick form seriously recommended to the consideration of both the clergy and laity of the Church of England : to which is added, a brief exhortation to the constant receiving of the Lords Supper.</title>
                  <author>Strong, Martin, b. 1663 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98039:1"/>
            <p>THE Indecency and Unlawfulneſs OF <hi>Baptizing Children</hi> IN PRIVATE, Without Neceſſity, and with the Publick Form. Seriouſly recommended to the Conſideration of both the Clergy and Laity of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> By <hi>Martin Strong,</hi> M. A. and Vicar of <hi>Yeovill</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi> To which is added, A brief Exhortation to the conſtant Receiving of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let all things be done decently, and in Order,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 14.40.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Adminiſtrari debent Sacramenta Coelu Eccleſiae &amp; non alibi; quando ſcilicet congregata eſt tota Eccleſia, vel illius pars magna, non Extra Coelum Eccleſiae.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gul. Bucani Inſtit. Theol. p. 607.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Bennet</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98039:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98039:2"/>
            <head>TO MY Honoured Friend and Patron Sir <hi>EDWARD PHELIPPS,</hi> Of <hi>MONTAC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TE.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I need not make Apologies for <hi>devoting</hi> the enſuing Papers to your <hi>Patronage;</hi> The <hi>triſte</hi> I confeſs is too mean to be preſented to ſo great a Name, but yet not to have done it, would have been both <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt.</hi> For 'twas compoſed for the benefit of a place, in which I am now happily fixed by your <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous</hi> and <hi>uncorrupted Charity,</hi> and in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, you made no other <hi>demands,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide a promiſe under my hand of <hi>living</hi> on the <hi>place,</hi> and taking <hi>care</hi> of the <hi>People.</hi> So far were you from making <hi>Merchandiſe</hi> of Souls, that you eſteem'd your right of Patronage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a <hi>ſacred truſt,</hi> for which you muſt give account to Almighty God; And may this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Example never want its followers. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that this <hi>Dedication</hi> may remain as a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:98039:3"/>Monument of my Gratitude, tho I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible it does not <hi>leſſen,</hi> but <hi>add</hi> to my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations; for the prefixing of your Name to this little <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> will, I doubt not, ſupply the <hi>want</hi> of a <hi>Character</hi> in its Author, and make it the more acceptable to the World.</p>
            <p>May all the Bleſſings of Heaven attend your Perſon, your Vertuous Lady, and every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your Family; May your <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwearied Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduity</hi> in ſerving your Country never want encouragment; May you continually enjoy the <hi>Advantages</hi> of doing good <hi>here</hi> on Earth, and receive a glorious reward for all in a <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter World.</hi> Theſe, Sir, ſhall be the conſtant Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obliged Humble Servant,</hi> M. Strong.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98039:3"/>
            <head>To my Beloved Pariſhioners THE Inhabitants of <hi>YEOVILL.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Dear Neighbours,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE deſign of this little Book is purely to reform (if poſſible) a <hi>Bad Cuſtom,</hi> which has too long prevailed among you, I mean. <hi>The Baptizing of your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Private,</hi> without Neceſſity and <hi>with the Publick Form;</hi> You all know I have already from the Pulpit told you both of the <hi>Indecency</hi> and <hi>Unlawfulneſs</hi> of this Practice, and ſolemnly proteſted to you that theſe were the only reaſons that prevailed with me not to comply with it; After all which I could not but hope, that you would have granted the requeſt I then made to you, and not have preſſed me any more to do a thing, which I had ſo evidently proved, to be againſt both <hi>your duty</hi> and <hi>my own.</hi> But to my great concern I have found it otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>In my own Vindication therefore, as well as for your Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, I have now committed what I formerly <hi>Preached,</hi> to the <hi>Preſs,</hi> with ſuch <hi>additions</hi> and <hi>alterations,</hi> as I thought ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make it fit for a Publick view: And that I might not be wanting in any part of my duty to you, I have printed theſe Papers to attend you at your houſes; hoping by this means to remove thoſe <hi>miſtakes</hi> and <hi>prejudices</hi> which <hi>ſome</hi> of you may have entertained in this matter, and to convince you fully, that the thing I <hi>here</hi> argue againſt, is really an <hi>Errour:</hi> Nor ſhould any thing leſs than this <hi>unhappy neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> have ever tempted me to appear in Print.</p>
            <p>In the management of this Argument, I have endeavoured to be both as <hi>Brief</hi> and <hi>Plain</hi> as poſſible, to ſet every thing in a clear and convincing light, and to come down to the meaneſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; which I deſire the Reader in general to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, and then I need not make Apologies for the Style, which might eaſily have been of another nature, but I was to conſult <hi>chiefly</hi> the capacities of my own People, and in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:98039:4"/>of <hi>Univerſal</hi> concern, I was willing <hi>All</hi> might underſtand me. As for other imperfectians, they may juſtly be imputed to my multiplicity of buſineſs, diverſions, and avocations in a large and populous Town; I am conſcious enough how many they are, but yet I have this ſatisfaction, that theſe papers had (at least as was protested) the <hi>Undiſſembled</hi> approbation of a worthy and judicious Friend, a perſon of a conſiderable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and Authority in the Church; for whoſe particular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, I cannot but take this occaſion of making a <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>grateful</hi> acknowledgment.</p>
            <p>And now (Neighbours) I have only one thing to deſire of you; that in reading this diſcourſe you would conſider every thing <hi>calmly</hi> and <hi>impartially,</hi> without <hi>paſſion, humour,</hi> or <hi>prejudice;</hi> Read it with that ſimplicity and indifferency of mind, that becomes humble, teachable and Charitable Chriſtians; Do not Nickname or miſconſtrue, what is by me <hi>well</hi> intended. Almighty God, the ſearcher of hearts, knows that I aim at nothing but your benefit, and Conviction: I have worded every thing after the mildest and moſt inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive manner I was able; If any thing ſeem <hi>cloſely</hi> or <hi>ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> ſpoken, 'tis no more than what I thought abſolutely neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the expoſing of the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of thoſe objections, which are uſually urged in juſtification of what I here oppoſe; And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, if you find that the <hi>Arguments</hi> here inſisted on, are ſuch as cannot be anſwered, then as you love your own Souls, let me beſeech you not <hi>wilfully</hi> to reſiſt the truth, but be <hi>glad</hi> and <hi>thankful</hi> rather, that you are freed from your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes.</p>
            <p>I have added at the end, a Brief Exhortation to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant receiving of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> which is a duty too much neglected <hi>amongſt you,</hi> as well as in <hi>other places.</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for all which I deſire nothing but your <hi>Prayers,</hi> as <hi>you</hi> ever have <hi>mine.</hi> And God Almighty follow you all with his Bleſſings, and give you hearts willing both to <hi>learn</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> the truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Sincere Friend and Servant,</hi> M. Srong.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98039:4"/>
            <head>The Indecency and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfulneſs of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing Children in Private, without Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, and with the Publick Form, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>'TIS a ſtrange prevailing power that <hi>Cuſtom</hi> has upon the minds of all mankind; The very <hi>Cuſtom</hi> and <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of dying, ſeems to have taken off the thoughts of death from the World; <hi>Manna</hi> itſelf was ſlighted when 'twas rained down every day; And that moſt ſacred and venerable rite of Chriſtianity, the bleſſed <hi>Sacrament</hi> itſelf, by being <hi>daily</hi> adminiſtred in the Primitive Church, in a little time began to be deſpis'd: And be the thing never ſo apparently <hi>vicious,</hi> or evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently <hi>unlawful,</hi> yet ſuch is the bewitching force of an habitual <hi>Cuſtomary</hi> Practice, that it hinders men from perceiving it, and begets ſuch inveterate <hi>prejudices</hi> in their minds, as <hi>darken</hi> the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and <hi>corrupt</hi> the <hi>Judgment,</hi> and bear down the force of the ſtrongeſt <hi>Arguments,</hi> and of the moſt convincing <hi>Reaſons</hi> in the World.</p>
            <p>Nothing but <hi>This</hi> could poſſibly have prevailed with ſo many members even of our own Communion, to perſevere ſo obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in Baptizing their Children in <hi>Private houſes, without</hi> any juſt Neceſſity, and <hi>with the Publick Form;</hi> a <hi>Cuſtom</hi> confeſſedly <hi>Indecent,</hi> and undeniably <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful;</hi> That it is ſo, is the deſign of this following <hi>Treatiſe</hi> to evince; and I hope to do it <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably,</hi> by inſiſting on theſe ſeveral Arguments.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That the Baptizing Children in Private houſes, is contrary to the nature and deſign of Chriſtian Baptiſm.</item>
               <item>2. 'Tis contrary to the conſtant and univerſal Practice of the Catholick Chriſtian Church in all ages.</item>
               <item>3. 'Tis contrary to the expreſs Laws and Rubrick of our own eſtabliſhed National Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. 'Tis contrary to every Miniſters ſolemn Promiſes and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions. And</item>
               <item>5. 'Tis Abſurd, and Irrational. If I can prove beyond de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial theſe ſeveral Aſſertions, I hope it will be granted, that I have ſufficiently performed my promiſed Undertaking, and that I had good reaſon for refuſing to comply with this <hi>Illegal</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98039:5"/>
            <p>But to prevent all miſtakes, it muſt be remembred, that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and Allowance is ſtill to be made for the Caſe of <hi>invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible</hi> Neceſſity, of extreme Sickneſs, and danger of Death; at which time the Church admits of <hi>Private Baptiſm,</hi> and has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed a particular Form for that purpoſe; of which I ſhall ſay more in its proper place. This being premiſed, I aſſert</p>
            <p>Firſt, That the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm in Private houſes, is contrary to the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Deſigns</hi> of Baptiſm; for Baptiſm is a great and moſt ſolemn part of Gods Publick Worſhip; 'Tis that Divine Sacrament by which we are entred and admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Chriſtian Church and Covenant, by which we are made members of that <hi>Holy Catholick Church,</hi> and united to that <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> and common Society of Chriſtians, which makes one fundamental Article of our Creed. Baptiſm is alſo an open and ſolemn profeſſion of our belief in the Sacred Trinity, Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, in whoſe names we are Baptized; but eſpecially 'tis a Publick declaration of our Faith in <hi>Jeſus</hi> the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator,</hi> an open acknowledgment to all the Woald that we hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily embrace that Goſpel and Religion, which Chriſt reveal'd from his Father to mankind, and which diſtinguiſhes us from <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Mahometans,</hi> and all other Religions in the World. For this reaſon 'twas, that the Font was always placed near the door or entrance into the Church,<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Dr.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricks Aqua Genitalis</note> to ſignifie to us that 'tis by Baptiſm we are firſt entred into the Chriſtian Faith, into the Religion and Church of Chriſt. Now all this evidently proves, that Baptiſm is not of a <hi>Private,</hi> but of a <hi>Publick</hi> Nature, and that its ends and deſigns are <hi>Publick;</hi> And from hence it as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently follows, that it ought to be adminiſtred <hi>according</hi> to its <hi>Nature,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks</hi> Rel. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemb. <hi>p. 291.</hi>
               </note> that is, not <hi>Privately,</hi> but in the <hi>Publick</hi> Aſſembly and Congregation of Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The force and reaſon of this Argument is plainly founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Apoſtolical precept, 1 Cor. 14.40. <hi>Let all things be done decently,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>and in order.</hi> If this be Scripture, and the word of God, it certainly obliges us, to perform all the Sacred and <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> offices of our Religion, with all that <hi>Decency,</hi> and <hi>Solemnity,</hi> that the <hi>Nature</hi> of the things, and the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of God requires. In this ſenſe the moſt learned <hi>Commentators</hi> underſtand the words; Nor can any other interpretation be put upon them, without offering a manifeſt violence to the deſign of the Apoſtle throughout that whole Chapter, which was to correct <hi>abuſes</hi> and <hi>indecencies</hi> in the ſervice of God, and to give ſuch ſtanding rules and general directions, as he thought neceſſary to be obſerved
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98039:5"/>in Gods Publick worſhip by all Chriſtian Congregations. This being granted, I now appeal to the ſenſe and reaſon of all the world, whether it be not more for the <hi>Decency</hi> and <hi>Solemnity</hi> of Chriſtian Baptiſm, to be adminiſtred in the <hi>Church</hi> and Houſe of God, than in a <hi>Private</hi> room of common and ordinary uſe? The Sacraments of our Religion are certainly the moſt ſolemn parts of it; We admit but <hi>two</hi> of theſe, and Baptiſm is <hi>one;</hi> And does it not beſt agree with the ſolemn Nature of this Sacrament, that it ſhould be Adminiſtred in the ſolemn place of Gods worſhip? Since Baptiſm is an <hi>open</hi> profeſſion of our Faith in Chriſt, how can this be duly performed in <hi>Private,</hi> or any where out of the <hi>Publick</hi> Aſſemblies of Chriſtians? And ſince Baptiſm is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to enter and admit us into the Church, what place can be ſo decent for its Adminiſtration, as the Church? To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we have Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> telling us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. Reform. Abridged.</hi> Lib. 2. p. 63.</note>
               <q rend="inline">That Baptiſm being the Admiſſion of a New Member to the Church, 'tis moſt ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the deſign of Baptiſm, to do it before the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; and withal adds, that the Liberty of baptizing in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, which was at firſt indulged by the Church, only as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for Weakneſs, is ſince become a <hi>Mark</hi> of <hi>Vanity</hi> and a piece of affected <hi>State.</hi>
               </q> If Baptiſm be deſigned to make us members of the Chriſtian Church, I would willingly be ſatisfied, how this can be <hi>decently</hi> performed out of the Church, and out of the preſence of the Church; or can any <hi>other</hi> place be ſo fit and convenient for ſo ſacred a thing, as the <hi>Place</hi> that is dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and devoted to the ſervice of God? Theſe are <hi>plain</hi> Queſtions I know, but I believe they are <hi>unanſwerable,</hi> and I leave them to the Conſcience of all Unprejudiced Readers; with this ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and earneſt Exhortation, <hi>viz.</hi> That they would not look on Baptiſm to be a trifling or inconſiderable thing, as if it were only the giving a <hi>Name</hi> to the Child, and no more; but that they would conſider it, as a moſt ſolemn part of Gods Worſhip, as that <hi>Divine Sacrament,</hi> by which their Children are dedicated to God, and to the Religon of Chriſt; The want of which Conſideration, I am convinced is the cauſe, why ſo many, <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe good and well meaning,</hi> Perſons, are ſo regardleſs, (provided it be done at all) <hi>how</hi> or <hi>where, in what place,</hi> or <hi>after what manner</hi> this ſacred duty is performed.</p>
            <p>I do not ſay that there is any <hi>Poſitive</hi> Holineſs in one place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove another, or that the place alone can ſanctify the worſhip performed in it, without other due Qualifications; but this I do affirm, and all the ſober part of Mankind did ever yet grant, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98039:6"/>as there is a <hi>Relative</hi> Holineſs in the Lords day, above other days of the Week, ſo there is at leaſt a <hi>Relative</hi> Holineſs in the Church above other places; both as 'tis ſet apart and conſecrated to the ſervice and worſhip of God, and as Almighty God is more <hi>eſpecially</hi> and <hi>immediately</hi> preſent in it; Upon this account it was, that the pious and Primitive Chriſtians,<note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Caves</hi> Primitive Chr. Chap. <hi>6.</hi> Part <hi>1.</hi> and Cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> always paid ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Reſpect and Veneration to the public places of Gods Worſhip, both at their firſt Entrance <hi>into,</hi> and all the while they continued <hi>in</hi> them. And for this reaſon 'tis, that the Public place of Gods Worſhip is in Scripture ſet forth by ſo many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Names and Titles; ſuch as are, the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,</hi> and the <hi>Sanctuary of the Lord;</hi> the <hi>Habitation of his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and the <hi>place where his Honor</hi> dwelleth; the <hi>Houſe of Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Church of God;</hi> All which things put together, do ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove, that there is at leaſt a <hi>Relative</hi> holineſs in the Church above other places, and that God is more immediately preſent there, to hear the Petitions, and to anſwer the Prayers of his humble Supplicants, and to give a due vertue and efficacy to his bleſſed Sacraments.</p>
            <p>But leſt I ſhould be thought to be <hi>ſingular</hi> in this opinion, I ſhall beg leave for the ſatisfaction of every <hi>unbyaſs'd</hi> Reader, to tranſcribe the words of a pious and learned Biſhop of this Church;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sparrow</hi> Bp. of <hi>Norwich</hi> in his <hi>Rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lé</hi> on the Com. Prayer, <hi>p. 371.</hi>
               </note> who ſpeaking of the Dedication of Churches and Chappels to Service of God, tells us, <q rend="inline">That our Prayers, and public Services, are moſt readily accepted in ſuch holy ſeparate places; and he proves it from 2 Chron. 7: 15. <hi>Now mine Eyes ſhall be open, and mine Ears attent to the Prayer in this place;</hi> which promiſe of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance belongs to any <hi>other</hi> place ſo dedicated and conſecrated to Gods holy Worſhip and Service, as was <hi>this</hi> houſe which <hi>Solomon</hi> built; for the reaſon which God gives of his gracious readineſs to hear the Prayer of <hi>that</hi> holy place, is in general <hi>this,</hi> v. 16. <hi>For now have I choſen and ſanctified this Houſe, that my Name might be there for ever; Now,</hi> that this houſe is dedicated and ſolemnly ſet apart by religious Rites and Prayers to my Service,<note place="margin">A quatenus ad omne valet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentia.</note>
                  <hi>now</hi> I have choſen it for mine.</q> And a little farther he adds, <q rend="inline">By the like reaſon whatſoever <hi>other</hi> place ſhall be dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to him, ſhall have the Eyes of God open, and his Ear attentive to the Prayer of it. And God Almighty promiſes as much, Exod. 20.24. <hi>In all places where I record my Name, I will come unto thee, and bleſs thee; that is,</hi> in <hi>all</hi> places dedicated to me, and my Service, and ſo made mine.</q> And a little farther (<hi>p.</hi> 385.) are theſe <hi>very remarkable</hi> words. <q rend="inline">The Church is the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98039:6"/> moſt convenient place for the ſervice of God, and adds much to the beauty of holineſs; And he that ſhould neglect that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and <hi>deſpiſing the Church,</hi> ſhould offer up the <hi>Publick</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (of which we have already proved Baptiſm to be a moſt ſolemn part) in <hi>Private,</hi> He would by ſo doing, ſin againſt that law of God, that ſays, <hi>Curſed be he that having a better Lamb in his flock, offers up to God a worſe,</hi> Mal. 1.14. For God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty muſt be ſerved with the <hi>beſt</hi> we have, otherwiſe we <hi>deſpiſe</hi> him; He that <hi>can</hi> have a <hi>Church,</hi> and will offer up the holy Service in a <hi>worſe place,</hi> Let him fear that Curſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This I think is home to the purpoſe, and an evident proof of my former aſſertion, from the plaineſt Texts of Scripture; and if it ſeem <hi>ſeverely ſpoken,</hi> let it be remembred that 'tis <hi>ſubſtantially proved;</hi> and that they are not mine, but a <hi>Reverend Prelates</hi> words of this Church, whoſe name and authority ought to be had in veneration by all its members; And would to God thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who contend ſo earneſtly for Baptizing their Children at home, without any juſt neceſſity, would conſider ſeriouſly, whether This be not very like that ſin, of <hi>deſpiſing the Church of God,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo ſeverely condemned in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 11.22. and not only making their own houſes <hi>equal</hi> to the Church, but in this reſpect <hi>preferring</hi> them before it.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole of this firſt Argument, I think it is undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably proved, that Baptiſm is not of a <hi>Private,</hi> but of a <hi>Publick</hi> Nature, and that the Church is the fitteſt and moſt decent place for the Adminiſtration of it; And therefore, that to adminiſter it in <hi>Private</hi> houſes, is both contrary to the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Deſigns</hi> of Baptiſm, and a plain tranſgreſſion of this precept of St. <hi>Paul, Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, To Adminiſter Baptiſm in Private houſes, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the conſtant practice of the Catholick Chriſtian Church in all ages? For the proof of this, I cannot take a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Method, than to give you the words of the judicious and learned <hi>Dr. Cave;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prim. Chriſt. c. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>311.</hi> pars pr.</note> who ſpeaking of the place where Baptiſm was <hi>anciently</hi> adminiſtred, tells us, <q rend="inline">That 'twas always as near as might be to the place of their <hi>Public</hi> Aſſemblies, and that 'twas ſeldom performed without the preſence of the Congregation; and that for very good reaſons, both as 'tis a principal act of Religious Worſhip, and as 'tis the initiating of Perſons into the Church, which therefore ought to be as <hi>Public</hi> as poſſible, that ſo the whole Congregation might be Spectators and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, of that Profeſſion and Engagement, which the baptized
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98039:7"/>Perſon then took upon him; And this the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſo zealouſly kept to, that the <hi>Trullan</hi> Council (<hi>Can.</hi> 59.) allows not Baptiſm to be adminiſtred in a Private Chappel or Oratory, but only in the Public Churches, puniſhing the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons offending in this particular with <hi>Depoſition</hi> from their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, if they were Clergy-men, and if Laity with <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For this reaſon they had their Baptiſteria or Fonts, built at firſt in ſome place near the Church, then in the Church <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Naz.</hi>
                  </note> Porch, till afterward they were placed in the Church itſelf.</q> This I think is very plain, and I have choſe to tranſcribe the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words of this reverend and learned Perſon, becauſe of his great Name and Eminency in the Church, eſpecially as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and diligent Inquirer into the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and Practice of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> of which this <hi>Book</hi> called <hi>Primitive Chriſtianity,</hi> is, amongſt the reſt, <hi>One</hi> illuſtrious proof.</p>
            <p>I was once thinking to add ſome other Obſervations of my own relating to this affair, But I <hi>ſince</hi> find this particular ſo large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unanſwerably proved by an ingenious Author who has lately writ on this very ſubject,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Arwaker</hi>'s Diſſuaſive from Baptizing Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Private, printed <hi>1687.</hi>
               </note> that, (becauſe I can add nothing new) I think it better to refer the inquiſitive Reader thither. The Book is licenſed by the <hi>Arch-Biſhop,</hi> and dedicated to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> Of both whoſe pious Endeavours to reform this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Custom,</hi> the Author gives us an account in his <hi>Epiſtle Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory;</hi> which I obſerve for this reaſon; that the Reader may know, that what I <hi>here</hi> write againſt has been condemned by the <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> and the whole <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in general. Whoever reads this little book from the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> to the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> page, will find it undeniably proved, that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>John</hi> and the Apoſtles themſelves baptized in Public; That both the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches do the ſame at this day, and that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Antient Fathers,<note place="margin">Juſtini Martyr, Tertullian; <hi>St.</hi> Athanaſius, Greg. Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen, <hi>St.</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>and</hi> Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom, <hi>St.</hi> Cyril.</note> and moſt learned Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Primitive Church, (whoſe Names are in the Margin) do all contend for Baptiſm in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic. He will find it proved that the <hi>Baptizing in Private houſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concilium. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans Meldenſe, &amp; Vernenſe. Caſſander, Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinian, Chamier, Vaſquez, &amp;c. Rel. Aſſemblys, <hi>p. 294.</hi>
               </note> has been often condemned and prohibited by whole Councils of Biſhops. And all this abundantly ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Teſtimonies of ſeveral other learned Writers, Men of great eſteem in their times. After all which I preſume we may very juſtly conclude with the learned Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi>
               <q rend="inline">That the Primitive Chriſtians always adminiſtred Baptiſm in <hi>Public</hi> places, and in the preſence of the Congregation, and never
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98039:7"/> that the Cuſtom thus continued in all the following Ages.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now the force of <hi>this</hi> Argument amounts to this; That in all caſes not <hi>poſitively</hi> determined by the Scripture, The Practice of the Primitive Church, is the ſureſt way for us to underſtand the Mind of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. For we cannot but think, that thoſe who convers'd with the Apoſtles, and with the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal men of the next ages, are the ſafeſt guides for us to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by, who live ſo remote from thoſe times. The Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Antient</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Tradition,</hi> has always been eſteemed ſacred and venerable, and whatever men may think <hi>now,</hi> yet to contradict the concurring Teſtimony and Practice of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church, was <hi>heretofore</hi> always thought, one of the greateſt Sins and Follies, that a Man could be guilty of. The Fathers themſelves do often confute Heretics of their times from preſcription, or the conſtant Traditionary <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of the Church. For tho we do not make Tradition to be a <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and Infallible Rule, as the Holy Oracles are; Yet, where the thing is doubtful or diſputable, where the Scripture is ſilent, there certainly the received Practice of the <hi>ancient <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Church, is the ſureſt guide for us to follow. There is an Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon us of the preſent times; to conform, as much as may be, to the <hi>Practice</hi> of the Univerſal Church, and to avoid <hi>Novelty,</hi> and <hi>Singularity</hi> in all things relating to the Worſhip of God; And therefore when we have ſo many plain Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Antiquity for baptizing in Public, and can find no one Church in the Chriſtian World that ever practiſed otherwiſe; when we have ſo many Ancient Fathers, Councils, and learned Writers, condemning Private Baptiſm, and pleading for that which is Public, and not any one ſingle Author produced of a contrary perſuaſion; There is certainly ſo much reſpect due to this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous Conſent</hi> of all our <hi>Pious Anceſtors,</hi> as proves it, to be very <hi>rude, indecent,</hi> and <hi>immodeſt</hi> for us of the preſent age, to contradict the general ſenſe of Chriſtianity, to affront and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Holy Catholic Church of Chriſt, by our contrary Practices, and to think our ſelves wiſer than all the Chriſtians that went before us; who for 1600 years together, have always Baptized in <hi>Public,</hi> and no doubt for good reaſons.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Adminiſtration of Baptiſm in Private houſes, without juſt Neceſſity, and with the Public Form, is contrary to the Expreſs <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Rubrick</hi> of our own National eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England.</hi> This is ſo plain and undeniable a Truth, that a modeſt man would think it needleſs to go about to prove
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98039:8"/>it, to any man who has got a Common-prayer book, and is but able to read the Rubrick without <hi>coloured Spectacles;</hi> which is as plain, and expreſs in this particular, as words can make it. For</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. The very appointing of two diſtinct Offices, and the calling one of them by the Name of <hi>Public,</hi> and the other by the Name of <hi>Private Baptiſm,</hi> is a plain demonſtration of the mind of the Church in this reſpect. For to what purpoſe has the Church compoſed a <hi>diſtinct</hi> Form of Baptiſm for caſes of ſickneſs and extreme Neceſſity, if ſhe had ever thought that the Public Form might have been <hi>then</hi> uſed as well? But let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſeveral Titles of thoſe two Offices; And the firſt we find is called, <hi>The Public Baptiſm of Infants, to be uſed in the Church;</hi> Now the very word, <hi>Public,</hi> proves that 'twas never intended to be uſed <hi>Privately;</hi> And the addition of that Clauſe, <hi>To be uſed in the Church,</hi> is an unanſwerable Argument, that it ought not to be uſed in <hi>Private</hi> houſes. But let us proceed from the <hi>Title</hi> to the <hi>Rubrick</hi> for <hi>Public Baptiſm;</hi> And the firſt thing we meet with is This.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline"> The People are to be admoniſhed that 'tis moſt convenient that Baptiſm ſhould not be adminiſtred, but upon Sundays and other Holy-days, when the moſt number of People come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. </q> And this our Church requires for two very good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which immediately follow; both which reaſons conclude ſtrongly for <hi>Public,</hi> and againſt <hi>Private</hi> Baptiſm. The firſt is</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline"> That the Congregation there preſent, may teſtify the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of them that be newly baptized, into the number of Chriſts Church.</q> The ſecond is</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline"> That by the Baptiſm of the Infant in the Church, every Perſon preſent may be put in mind of his own ſolemn vow and profeſſion made to God in his own Baptiſm.</q> To this purpoſe the learned Dr. <hi>Comber</hi> tells us, <q rend="inline">That Infants ougut to be brought to the Church,<note place="margin">Diſcourſe upon the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer. <hi>p. 338.</hi>
                  </note> that there may be many Witneſſes of this ſolemn act, and that <hi>others</hi> may be put in mind of their Vow, as alſo becauſe they may be admitted Members of our Religious Aſſemblies in the <hi>proper</hi> place.</q> And he that has a mind to ſee farther, how much Public Baptiſm tends to the Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Church, Let him read Dr. <hi>Sherlocks Rel. Aſſemblies</hi> p. 293.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and conſider withal, how the Cuſtom of Baptizing in Private can be reconciled with that Precept of St. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.26. <hi>Let all things be done to Edifying;</hi> that is, in all acts of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98039:8"/>Worſhip, let every thing be ſo performed, as may tend moſt to the benefit and advantage of others;<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Hammond in locum,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Beveridge</hi> his Sermons on this Text.</note> which is the Paraphraſe of a very learned man on the words.</p>
            <p>In the third Section or Paragraph of the Rubrick before Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Baptiſm, <q rend="inline">The Godfathers, and Godmothers, and the People with the Children are required to be ready at the <hi>Font;</hi>
               </q> Now, I hope, this may paſs for a plain Command for the bringing of Children to the Church; for where elſe is the <hi>Font?</hi> Are there any in <hi>Private</hi> houſes? Or how can Children be brought to the <hi>Font,</hi> if they are not firſt brought to the <hi>Church,</hi> where <hi>alone</hi> the <hi>Font</hi> is placed? But this is not all, the <hi>time</hi> is alſo ſpecified as well as the Place; <q rend="inline">The Children are to be ready at the Font immediately after the ſecond Leſſon at Morning or Evening Prayer,</q> which ſtill farther concludes for its being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Church, where <hi>alone</hi> the <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Leſſons</hi> are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally read; And all this is abundantly confirmed by that which follows, <hi>viz. And the Prieſt ſtanding there, at the Font, ſhall ſay,</hi> &amp;c. So far I think nothing can be more plain or undeniable. But let us go on to the <hi>Office</hi> for <hi>Private Baptiſm of Children in houſes,</hi> for ſo 'tis called.</p>
            <p>The very <hi>Name</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> of which, is enough to ſatisfy any ſober man, that this <hi>alone,</hi> and not the <hi>Public Form</hi> is to be uſed in <hi>Houſes.</hi> But the Rubrick is more expreſs.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline"> There in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Paragraph, the Curates or Miniſters of every Pariſh are required often to admoniſh and warn the People, that without great Cauſe and Neceſſity, to be approved by the Curates themſelves, they procure not their Children to be baptized at home;</q> And in Obedience to this <hi>Command</hi> of the Church, I do now deſire and beſeech you of my Care not to do it; But when need ſhall compel, then the Rubrick expreſly orders, that Baptiſm be adminiſtred on <hi>This Faſhion,</hi> namely by that Form of <hi>Private</hi> Baptiſm, which there follows, and not by the <hi>Publick</hi> Form.</p>
            <p>So that, as the <hi>Ancient</hi> Church never did, ſo neither does the <hi>Preſent</hi> Church of <hi>England</hi> allow of any <hi>Private Baptiſm,</hi> except in danger of death; and in ſuch a caſe ſhe has provided a Form for that purpoſe, and required the uſe of that alone. And upon the whole, I think it undeniably follows, that To Baptize Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in <hi>Private,</hi> with the <hi>Publick</hi> Form, and without <hi>juſt Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> is, (as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> tells us, <hi>Rel. Aſſemblies p.</hi> 295.) <q rend="inline">a plain tranſgreſſion of the <hi>Rule,</hi> and therefore ſuch a diſorder, as no man ſhould be guilty of, who profeſſes himſelf a Member of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98039:9"/>our Church; 'Tis a plain breach of the expreſs <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> of our own <hi>Communion,</hi> which was the thing to be proved.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now as for this Argument, it equally concerns all in general, who own themſelves of the Church of <hi>England, Rich</hi> and <hi>Poor, Laity,</hi> as well as <hi>Clergy.</hi> For by the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article of our Church, we all profeſs to believe, <q rend="inline">That the Church has full power to decree and command all ſuch Rites and Ceremonies, as are not contrary to the word of God;</q> Nor did ever any yet deny this power, but thoſe who were profeſſed Diſſenters from us, and againſt them it has been <hi>largely,</hi> and <hi>unanſwerably</hi> proved, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned Divines of this Church, whoſe Names I have ſet in the Margin,<note place="margin">By Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonab. of Separation. Dr. <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi> in his Vindication of that book; and in his Anſwer to the Proteſtant Reconciler.
<p>By Dr. <hi>Goodman</hi> in his Compaſſ. Enquiry.</p>
                  <p>By Dr. <hi>Scot,</hi> Chriſtian Life, Part <hi>2.</hi> Vol. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>433.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And inſtead of all by the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable <hi>Hooker</hi> Eccl. Polity, <hi>Lib. 3.</hi> and others.</p>
               </note> if any one pleaſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult them.</p>
            <p>Now then, thus I argue; if the Church has Power to make Laws in things indifferent, and not forbidden by the Scriptures, it hence neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily follows, that 'tis our abſolute duty to obey and ſubmit to thoſe Laws, when once they are made: For a <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>Command,</hi> neceſſarily infers the <hi>duty</hi> of <hi>Obedience,</hi> theſe are <hi>Relative</hi> things, the <hi>one</hi> of which unavoidably follows from the <hi>other;</hi> Nor can we <hi>diſobey</hi> the <hi>Lawful</hi> Commands of the Church, without <hi>diſobeying Heaven</hi> at the ſame time, and Chriſt Jeſus himſelf, from whom, as from a Supream Head, the Church has received this <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power; and how then can it become any true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church, to be thus <hi>wilfully</hi> guilty of trangreſſing its plaineſt Laws? Or why ſhould any pious and genuine Son of the Church, carry himſelf thus refractory to his ſpiritual Mother? Or can there be any thing more <hi>abſurd,</hi> than to profeſs to believe, <hi>that the Church has Power to make Laws in indifferent things,</hi> and yet whenever thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> come to be <hi>obeyed,</hi> to <hi>diſpute,</hi> and <hi>deny</hi> its Authority? Eſpecially conſidering, how pious and primitive a duty this is, and what great reaſon the Church has to require it. This certainly is not to <hi>do things according to Order,</hi> that is (as the great Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> tells us upon the place) <hi>According to the Order and Direction of the Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Rich. Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks <hi>Practical Chriſtian,</hi> p. 85</note> I know not what low thoughts men may <hi>now</hi> have of this Diſobedience, But I am ſure the pious D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Sherlock</hi> had another ſenſe of things, when he made <hi>this</hi> a part of his Form of Confeſſion of Sin.</p>
            <q>
               <p> I have not made Conſcience to obey the Laws and Orders of thy Church, whether Univerſal or particular, not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98039:9"/>or ſubmitting to the Authority of Either; and I am juſtly therefore to be rankt amongſt Publicans and Sinners.</p>
               <p> My Ghoſtly Fathers and Paſtors, in the ſeveral orders of Biſhop, Prieſt and Deacon, I have disbelieved, diſreſpected, diſobeyed, in their Callings, in their Admonitions for my Souls health. I have hated him that reproveth in the Gate, I have hardned my heart, and refuſed when admoniſhed, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from the Errour of my ways.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Nor is this a Law of the <hi>Church</hi> only, but of the <hi>Civil State</hi> too, The whole Rubrick is confirmed by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> as well as by <hi>Convocation;</hi> and the Act of Uniformity before our <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Books,</hi> expreſly injoyns under the ſevereſt Penalty, that <hi>No other Form of Prayer or Adminiſtration of the Sacraments be uſed, beſide that which is ſet forth and allowed by that Book.</hi> So that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever refuſes Obedience to thoſe Laws of the <hi>Church</hi> concerning Baptiſm, does at the ſame time diſobey a Law of the <hi>State</hi> too, his <hi>Civil</hi> as well as his <hi>Spiritual</hi> Parents and Governors; and if this be not a plain Breach of the fifth Commandment, Let every mans Conſcience judge.</p>
            <p>There is, I foreſee, one <hi>fond</hi> pretence, that may poſſibly be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to this Argument, and that is the <hi>preſent Act of Toleration,</hi> or <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> which may be thought to diſcharge the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the Eſtabliſhed Laws of the Church. But in anſwer to this vain Cavil, I ſay,</p>
            <p>Firſt, That I write not at preſent to thoſe who are <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from the Church, but to thoſe who profeſs themſelves <hi>Members</hi> of our own Communion; and what have ſuch to do with the <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Let the Act it ſelf be read, and 'twill appear that the <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> was intended only for the Eaſe of thoſe few (for I verily believe they are not many) who are <hi>ſincerely</hi> perſuaded in their Conſciences, that 'tis not <hi>Lawful</hi> for them to <hi>obey</hi> the Orders, or joyn in the Worſhip of the <hi>Establiſhed</hi> Religion; Now what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſervice the Plea of a <hi>Toleration</hi> may do ſuch miſtaken Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet certainly it looks very unaccountable in one of our <hi>own Communion,</hi> to make this pretence in excuſe for <hi>his</hi> Diſobedience to <hi>thoſe Laws,</hi> and to <hi>that Conſtitution,</hi> to which he himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs. I envy no man the <hi>Liberty of Conſcience;</hi> My Charity is Univerſal, I heartily wiſh well to, and pray for all the World; But the <hi>Toleration</hi> is for <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> not for us; We have ſtill (bleſſed be God) the ſame Church, the ſame Public Liturgy, the ſame Articles, Canons, and Conſtitutions eſtabliſhed by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98039:10"/>Law of the Land, by ſeveral Acts of Parliament which ſtand yet unrepealed; And therefore <hi>our Obedience</hi> is ſtill as due to thoſe Laws, as ever; Nor can the <hi>Toleration</hi> with any ſhew of Modeſty or Reaſon be thought to excuſe <hi>us,</hi> ſo long as we own our ſelves <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as of a <hi>good</hi> and an <hi>Orthodox Communion.</hi> But ſuppoſe I were concern'd with a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Diſſenter,</hi> yet I might juſtly anſwer,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all that any <hi>Toleration</hi> in the World <hi>does,</hi> or can do, is to excuſe only from the <hi>Penalty,</hi> not at all from the <hi>fault</hi> of Diſobedience to the Laws and Orders, of an <hi>Eſtabliſhed Lawful</hi> Communion; it gives a Liberty of <hi>Impunity</hi> 'tis true, (whether <hi>juſtly</hi> or <hi>unjuſtly</hi> I will not now diſpute) but not of <hi>juſtification;</hi> it takes away the <hi>civil Puniſhment,</hi> but it can never take away the <hi>Sin</hi> of Non-conformity or Diſobedience; my reaſon for it is this, becauſe <hi>theſe</hi> are Sins forbidden by the plain Laws of God, which no Laws of Man can alter or diſpenſe with. For every <hi>Orthodox</hi> and <hi>lawfully conſtituted</hi> Church, has a full power from <hi>Chriſts</hi> own <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> to make Canons and Conſtitutions for its own Regulation, for the ſecurity and preſervation of its own Peace and good Order; And this lays a ſufficient Obligation on all Chriſtians to obey thoſe Laws, tho there ſhould be no <hi>Civil Authority</hi> to back and enforce them; The <hi>Church,</hi> conſidered as a <hi>Church,</hi> is a <hi>diſtinct</hi> body, and has a <hi>diſtinct</hi> Government inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in it ſelf, without any regard had to the <hi>State;</hi> And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all diſobedience to the Lawful Commands of the Church, is an Evil in it ſelf, <hi>Morally</hi> and <hi>intrinſecally</hi> ſinful, and therefore can never be altered by any <hi>Humane</hi> Diſpenſation or Toleration. Hence we find the Primitive Chriſtians decrying <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and branding it with the moſt odious Characters, before there were any <hi>Civil</hi> Laws in <hi>Defence</hi> of Chriſtianity, nay when all the <hi>Civil</hi> Laws were <hi>againſt</hi> it; as well <hi>before</hi> the Empire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſtian, and again in the intervals of Perſecution, as when Chriſtianity was <hi>Eſtabliſhed</hi> by a Law. So the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> were accounted <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> by the Primitive Chriſtians, as well under thoſe <hi>temporal</hi> Princes that <hi>favoured,</hi> as under thoſe who <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted</hi> them; <hi>Arianiſm</hi> was condemned, as well under <hi>Conſtantius</hi> and <hi>Valens,</hi> who <hi>countenanced,</hi> as under <hi>Conſtantine</hi> who <hi>oppoſed</hi> it; ſo that tho a Toleration do take away <hi>Civil Penalties,</hi> yet the Laws of God, and of Scripture that require <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Communion</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance</hi> with an eſtabliſhed <hi>Orthodox</hi> Church, do ſtand ſtill uncan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell'd, and in as much force as ever. If any one doubt the truth
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98039:10"/>of this, Let him only read the ingenious M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Norris</hi> his <hi>Charge of Schiſm continued,</hi> and if he can <hi>fairly</hi> anſwer what that <hi>learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> there urges, in defence of this Aſſertion, I promiſe him I will inſtantly give up the Cauſe, and become his Proſelite.</p>
            <p>There is a paſſage in the learned Dr. <hi>Stillingfleets</hi> Sermon of the <hi>Miſchief of Separation,</hi> ſo <hi>appoſite</hi> to our preſent Argument, that I cannot forbear ſetting it down; 'Tis Page the 45<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, in theſe words; <q rend="inline">Let us who continue in the Communion of our Church, <hi>walk by the ſame Rule and mind the ſame things;</hi> While we keep to <hi>one Rule,</hi> all People know what it is to be of our Church; if men ſet up their <hi>own Fancies</hi> above the Rule, they charge it with <hi>Imperfection;</hi> if they do not <hi>obey</hi> the Rule, they make themſelves wiſer than thoſe that made it; It hath not been the <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Rules</hi> of our <hi>Church,</hi> which have ever given ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the Enemies of it, but the <hi>Indiſcretion</hi> of ſome, in going <hi>beyond</hi> them, and the <hi>Inconſtancy</hi> of others, in not <hi>holding</hi> to them.</q> This being the Judgment and Opinion of ſo great a man, and of ſo <hi>pacifick</hi> a Temper, deſerves a ſerious Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by all who wiſh well to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Baptizing Children in <hi>Private,</hi> by the <hi>Public</hi> Form, is contrary to every Miniſters ſolemn <hi>Promiſes</hi> and <hi>Subſcriptions;</hi> For the 36<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Canon</hi> of our Church, Every Miniſter is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, both at his receiving of Orders, and at his Admiſſion to any <hi>Benefice</hi> or <hi>Living,</hi> to make this Promiſe, and to ſubſcribe it with his own hand, in theſe very words, <hi>viz. That he himſelf will uſe the Form preſcribed in the book of Common Prayer, both in Public Prayer, and in the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and none other.</hi> And now I appeal to the ſenſe of all the world, whether that Miniſter who uſes that Form of <hi>Public</hi> Baptiſm in <hi>Private</hi> Houſes, which is <hi>preſcribed</hi> to be uſed in the <hi>Church,</hi> does not break this Promiſe; And whether he who does <hi>not</hi> in <hi>Private</hi> houſes, uſe the Form <hi>Preſcribed</hi> for that purpoſe, does not do the ſame? Does ſuch a Man uſe the <hi>Form preſcribed, by the Book of Common Prayer, and none other,</hi> as he promiſed, and ſubſcribed? Perhaps it will be ſaid, that he uſes the ſame words, tho in a different Place; But ſtill I anſwer, That this is not the <hi>Form preſcribed by the Book of Common Prayer;</hi> The Form preſcribed is perfectly of <hi>Another Nature;</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> has compoſed two Forms for <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> of Infants; the one for the <hi>Church,</hi> the other for <hi>Private</hi> houſes; the one for <hi>ordinary</hi> and common caſes, the other for the <hi>extraordinary</hi> caſes of ſickneſs, and neceſſity; Now he that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98039:11"/>
               <hi>confounds</hi> theſe two <hi>Offices,</hi> which the Church has made <hi>diſtinct</hi> and wholy <hi>omitting</hi> that <hi>Form</hi> which is deſigned for <hi>Private, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> that in <hi>Private,</hi> which is <hi>commanded</hi> to be uſed in <hi>Public,</hi> that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon does not uſe <hi>the Form preſcribed by the Book of Common Prayer, and none other,</hi> but <hi>perfectly another,</hi> than what is commanded. If any one in the World can deny this aſſertion, or without <hi>Tricks</hi> and <hi>Fallacies</hi> fairly juſtify this Practice from <hi>Breach</hi> of <hi>Promiſe,</hi> I will never more truſt my diſcurſive Faculty ſo long as I live; can any thing be more <hi>indiſputably</hi> clear? If to doubt in this caſe, be not to <hi>ſeek Knots in a Bulruſh,</hi> I know not what is.</p>
            <p>This Argument very nearly concerns us of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and we ſhould all do well ſeriouſly to conſider it; and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our own <hi>undue</hi> Compliances in this reſpect, are made uſe of by the <hi>Laity,</hi> as the greateſt Argument for the Continuance of this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> Practice. But if the moſt ſolemn <hi>Promiſes,</hi> and repeated <hi>Subſcriptions</hi> ſignify any thing, we are all certainly bound to do our utmoſt for the reforming of this <hi>unhappy</hi> Cuſtom; in doing of which there would be far leſs difficulty than now there is, were we our ſelves <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous</hi> in the Attempt, were we <hi>All</hi> reſolved to be juſt to our own Engagements, and would not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine each others Endeavours, by our <hi>contrary</hi> Practices. 'Tis plain, we are not left at Liberty to do as we pleaſe in this caſe; we are bound by Laws, by Promiſes and Subſcriptions; And when the Laity know and conſider this, I cannot but hope, that they will think the <hi>better,</hi> and not the <hi>worſe</hi> of us, for being juſt to our Rule, and true to our Promiſes; Nor will they be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable as to expect our compliance in a thing ſo <hi>manifeſtly unlawful;</hi> Much leſs conceive any <hi>Pet</hi> or <hi>Prejudice</hi> againſt us, only becauſe we cannot make the plaineſt Laws of the <hi>Church,</hi> and our own Promiſes too, bend and bow to their humors. And ſince the <hi>London</hi> Clergies Practice, is moſt taken notice of in this affair, it would be happy if they would joyn with us, in this Reformation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Form of Public Baptiſm is ſo compoſed, that it cannot be uſed in Private Houſes, without manifeſt Abſurdities, which is another demonſtration that the Church never intended it ſhould be ſo uſed. The forementioned M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Arwaker</hi> reckons up <hi>four</hi> ſeveral inſtances of this Nature in the Office of Public Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, where he that has a mind may ſee them (<hi>pag.</hi> 29.) I ſhall only mention <hi>One</hi> at preſent, and that is in the Preface to the Baptiſmal Covenant, in theſe words— <hi>Dearly beloved, Ye have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98039:11"/>brought this Child here to be Baptized.</hi> How can <hi>this</hi> be truly or rationally ſpoken, when inſtead of the <hi>Childs</hi> being <hi>brought</hi> by the Sureties, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> himſelf comes home to the houſe, and is <hi>brought</hi> into the very <hi>Chamber</hi> were the <hi>Child</hi> was born? We have already proved that the <hi>Church</hi> at the beginning of this Office requires the Child to be brought to the <hi>Font,</hi> and that the Prieſt ſtanding at the <hi>Font</hi> ſhall ſay— From whence 'tis manifeſt, that by the word <hi>(Here)</hi> in this place, is meant the <hi>Church</hi> where alone the <hi>Font</hi> ſtands; And how then can the <hi>Minister</hi> in the very place where the <hi>Child</hi> was born, ſay to the Sureties, <hi>Ye have brought this Child here</hi> (viz. <hi>to the Font</hi>) <hi>to be Baptized:</hi> Or ought he not rather to alter the words to a quite contrary ſenſe, and ſay, <hi>Ye have brought me here to baptize this Child;</hi> For <hi>this</hi> is true, and proper, but the <hi>former</hi> is evidently falſe and abſurd; and the Abſurdity is ſo plain, that I am verily perſwaded, that he that does not perceive it, 'Tis not becauſe He cannot, but becauſe He <hi>will not</hi> underſtand it. Now whether it becomes either Miniſter or People to uſe ſuch groſs <hi>Abſurdities</hi> in ſo ſolemn a part of Gods ſacred Worſhip, is a Queſtion, to which I would beg a ſerious Anſwer.</p>
            <p>There is the ſame <hi>Abſurdity</hi> in the Office for <hi>Churching Women,</hi> when 'tis uſed in <hi>Private houſes;</hi> The very Title proves this Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice to be <hi>abſurd;</hi> It ought to be called <hi>Chambering</hi> or <hi>Houſeing</hi> of Women, But <hi>Churching</hi> of them it can never be in any place <hi>out of the Church.</hi> But not to inſiſt on that, the Rubrick before this Office ſays, <hi>The Woman ſhall come into the Church, decently apparalled, and there ſhall kneel down in ſome convenient Place,</hi> &amp;c. than which, no command can be more plain; The Rubrick at the End of the Office, directs the Woman, <hi>to receive the Holy Communion, if there be any,</hi> which ſtill farther argues it to be done in the Church; and the laſt Verſe of the Pſalm appointed to be read in this Office, makes the Abſurdity undeniable: 'Tis this, <hi>I will pay my Vows now</hi>— <hi>In the Courts of the Lords houſe;</hi> How can <hi>this</hi> be ſaid in any Private Chamber? Was ever any Place beſide the <hi>Church,</hi> called <hi>the Lords houſe?</hi> Or can any other Place be ſo called, without a manifeſt and daring Abſurdity? An Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty too groſs to be offer'd to the great God in return for a Mercy, which deſerves not only a <hi>Private</hi> Acknowledgment,<note place="margin">See Bp. <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and Dr. <hi>Comber</hi> on this Office.</note> but a moſt ſolemn Thankſgiving, in the <hi>Public</hi> Aſſembly of Chriſtians; which is both a <hi>greater Honour,</hi> and more <hi>acceptable</hi> to God, than any <hi>Private</hi> returns can be.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98039:12"/>
            <p>And now a modeſt man would think, that after all this, there ſhould be no poſſible <hi>Objectious,</hi> againſt ſo <hi>undeniable</hi> a truth; Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> tells us (<hi>Rel. Aſſemb. p.</hi> 290.) <q rend="inline">
                  <hi>That he could never hear any thing that deſerved a ſerious Anſwer:</hi>
               </q> But leſt the Pretences ſhould be thought unanſwerable, let us hear what they are.</p>
            <p>And the firſt grand Pretence is <hi>Cuſtom;</hi> 'Tis objected to us, that 'tis generally practiſed in moſt parts of the Kingdom; and by many great and eminent <hi>Divines</hi> of the City of <hi>London</hi> too, and therefore why may it not be continued? This Objection, tho it make a great deal of Noiſe, yet it ſignifies juſt nothing, as will be evident to any one, that conſiders theſe things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That however prevailing this <hi>Cuſtom</hi> now is, yet 'tis but of very late date, even in this Church; D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sherlock</hi> tells us (<hi>Rel. Aſſemb.</hi> p. 290) That this unhappy <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> was begun by as unhappy a Cauſe; Namely by our late <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> and a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Uſurpation; When our Laws were all ſubverted, and our Religion ruined; When the Orthodox Clergy were all turned a begging, and their Churches uſurped by their Enemies, then 'twas that the Loyal Party, being firſt <hi>baniſhed</hi> from the Church, were <hi>forced</hi> and <hi>compelled</hi> to Baptize their Children in their own Houſes; There was a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> then of doing it <hi>privately,</hi> or not at all; But this <hi>Neceſſity</hi> is now removed, our Churches now (thanks be to Almighty God) are at Liberty; And therefore this can be no Argument to excuſe us; But it becomes us rather to abhor a Cuſtom brought into the Church by ſuch <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly</hi> means, and to remember that our Forefathers would have been <hi>glad,</hi> and <hi>thankful</hi> too, to have injoyed that Liberty and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of bringing their Children to the <hi>Church,</hi> which we now deſpiſe.</p>
            <p>And yet 'tis very obſervable, that even in thoſe times, when the Common-Prayer Book was aboliſhed, and the Presbyrerian <hi>Directory</hi> eſtabliſhed in its room, by what was then called an <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament, Anno</hi> 1644. Even that very <hi>Directory</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decrees, <q rend="inline">That <hi>Baptiſm is</hi> not <hi>to be adminiſtred in Private places, or privately, but in the place of Public Worſhip, and in the Face of the Congregation,</hi>
               </q> as may be ſeen (<hi>p.</hi> 19) And this is the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable becauſe the Compilers of this <hi>Directory</hi> do in their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face declare, that they compoſed and agreed upon it, <hi>after ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and frequent calling upon the Name of God, and after much conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, not with Fleſh and Blood, but with Gods holy word.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98039:12"/>
            <p>'Tis well known that our Brethren of this Perſwaſion were always great Enemies to all <hi>Needleſs</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious Ceremonies</hi> in the Worſhip of God; from whence I infer, that even in <hi>their Opinion,</hi> The Adminiſtration of Baptiſm in the Public place of Gods Worſhip, is not a <hi>Needleſs Ceremony,</hi> but a <hi>Neceſſary Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance</hi> to the due and decent Performance of that divine <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament;</hi> What their <hi>Practice now</hi> is, it concerns not me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, 'tis plain <hi>This</hi> is their <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>This</hi> their <hi>Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Tho many eminent Divines, and particularly of <hi>London,</hi> do comply with this <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> yet ſome others no leſs emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent refuſe to do it. D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sherlock,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Arwaker</hi> have both writ expreſly againſt it; And all thoſe who have writ any thing in Defence of the Churches Power to make Laws in things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, have in effect done the ſame; for if the Church has Power to <hi>command, with Submiſſion,</hi> it muſt be our duty to <hi>obey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Tho this had been a <hi>Custom</hi> of <hi>longer date,</hi> and cauſed by <hi>better means,</hi> yet what ſignifies a <hi>bad</hi> Cuſtom againſt a <hi>known Rule,</hi> and the expreſs Laws of the Church? What Sins, what Errors and Offences may not be juſtified, if <hi>Custom</hi> be allowed as an Arguument for them? So Swearing is a <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is a <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> and I have known ſome Perſons ſo impudent, as to urge the <hi>Commoneſs</hi> of thoſe crying ſins in their <hi>Defence.</hi> But is it any leſſening of a Sin, that a great many are guilty of it? Certainly he who commanded us <hi>not to follow a Multitude to do Evil,</hi> thought otherwiſe. <hi>Sodom</hi> was deſtroyed, not the <hi>later</hi> but the <hi>ſooner,</hi> for that they were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally</hi> wicked. I ſhall always be glad to follow a <hi>good Example</hi> in <hi>any Perſon;</hi> but in that which is amiſs, the Greateſt Man in the World ſhall never be the Pattern of my imitation; I reverence the Perſons, and Writings too of ſeveral <hi>great</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> men, (whoſe <hi>Practice</hi> we are upbraided with in this Particular) as much as any man living; but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering what ill uſe is made of their Examples, I heartily wiſh, that they would either joyn with us, in reforming this <hi>bad Custom,</hi> or elſe condeſcend ſo far, as to let us know how it may be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. In ſhort, I think the Queſtion in this caſe, ought to be, whether the Cuſtom of Baptizing Children in <hi>Private,</hi> without <hi>juſt Neceſſity,</hi> and by the <hi>Public Form,</hi> be a <hi>decent,</hi> or <hi>indecent,</hi> a <hi>Lawful,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> Cuſtom? Now that 'tis both <hi>indecent</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful</hi> I have undeniably proved in the foregoing Diſcourſe; And therefore all that can follow, from its being a <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98039:13"/>this, that the longer it has been continued, the more has been the fault, and the ſooner it ought to be amended.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen how this Cuſtom came firſt to be <hi>introduced;</hi> and 'tis no difficult matter to gueſs at the cauſes of its <hi>Continuance;</hi> Some perhaps have complyed with it, out of an <hi>immoderate</hi> love to their own Eaſe, and an Unwillingneſs to be at the pains and trouble of reforming a bad Cuſtom, tho they knew it to be <hi>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others it may be, have been tempted to it by <hi>Poverty,</hi> which has made them forget the Dignity, and Sacredneſs of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Character, by ſacrificing both their Duty and Promiſes at once to a piece of Gold or Silver, and to be guilty of ſuch <hi>ſordid mercenary</hi> Compliances, as to <hi>ſell their Birth right,</hi> I mean the Dignity of the Prieſthood, <hi>for a Meſs of Pottage.</hi> I wiſh this <hi>thing</hi> called <hi>Intereſt,</hi> has not too much prevailed with ſome, who can pretend no real want of any thing, which makes the crime ſo much the more unpardonable; tho after all it is to be feared, that whatever is thus <hi>unlawfully</hi> got, is no better than <hi>(Aurum Tholoſanum) Money put into a Bag with Holes,</hi> and like the Coal which the Eagle ſtole from the Altar, that conſumed both her Neſt, and her young to Aſhes.</p>
            <p>Others perhaps have done it, purely out of an <hi>obliging diſpoſition,</hi> and upon <hi>prudential</hi> Conſiderations, thinking it the beſt way to break a bad Cuſtom where they have found it, not <hi>too raſhly,</hi> but <hi>by Degrees;</hi> to lay it aſide by that means, as decently, with as <hi>little</hi> noiſe and diſguſt, and with as <hi>much</hi> ſatisfaction to their Neighbors as poſſible; Hoping by this Condeſcenſion to win their good Opinion, and in time to bring them by thoſe <hi>mild Methods</hi> to a through Conformity to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and their <hi>own</hi> Duty; which was no more than the great St. <hi>Paul</hi> did toward <hi>the Jews,</hi> in laying aſide the old <hi>Moſaical Rites</hi> and <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This has been <hi>my own</hi> caſe, and I verily believe the <hi>Caſe</hi> of a great many of my Brethren; And that the continuance of this Unlawful Cuſtom, is to be imputed, <hi>not</hi> to the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the thing it ſelf, but to ſome <hi>one</hi> or <hi>other</hi> of theſe cauſes. I am fully convinced from hence; becauſe even of thoſe Miniſters, who <hi>do,</hi> or <hi>have</hi> complyed with this Practice, I never could hear any <hi>one</hi> pretend to juſtify it, but frankly confeſs, it ought not to be done. And thus I think I have abundantly anſwered that clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Objection from <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> which indeed did not deſerve
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98039:13"/>the Expence of ſo much Ink and paper, as has been thrown away upon it, but ſome things muſt be anſwered, tho not for their <hi>real weight,</hi> yet becauſe of the <hi>Noiſe</hi> they make in the World; tho at beſt it is but like the ſound of an empty Veſſel; <hi>Sonus, &amp; prate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea nihil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I am afraid, Another thing which keeps ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from bringing their Children to the Church to be baptized, is <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs;</hi> Such Perſons look upon it as a piece of <hi>State,</hi> to have their Children baptized at home, and fancy that ſomething more ought to be done for <hi>them,</hi> than for <hi>poorer People;</hi> Now I readily grant that there is a different <hi>civil</hi> reſpect due to men according to their <hi>various</hi> Degrees and Qualities, and ſo there is to <hi>Friends</hi> the ſame, and God forbid but in all <hi>lawful</hi> things, they ſhould have it to the utmoſt Degrees in which 'tis due; (And that I may not be condemned neither of <hi>Incivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> nor <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> which I naturally abhor, I here <hi>publickly</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that I ſhall always look upon it, as my great <hi>unhappineſs,</hi> that ſome of thoſe whom I have been forced to deny in this matter, were of this Number) But it muſt be conſidered, that in matters of <hi>abſolute duty</hi> (ſuch as this is proved to be) all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are Equal, and in ſuch caſes there ought to be no <hi>reſpect</hi> of Perſons; Rich and Great Perſons are no more <hi>above</hi> their duty, than Poor and Mean men are <hi>below</hi> it; If it be a <hi>Duty,</hi> 'tis ſo to all alike; Even a Heathen <hi>Pericles</hi> could ſay, when his Friend deſired him <hi>to</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Arch. Atticae Lib. 3. cap. 3. <hi>Hence the Prov.</hi> Amicus uſque ad Aras. Omne animi vitium, &amp;c. <hi>Juven. Sat.</hi> 8.</note>
               <hi>teſtify a Lye; I am your Friend as far as Honeſty and a good Conſcience will permit;</hi> And I muſt take leave to ſay, that he is not a Friend, that deſires more. And a Pagan Poet has taught us, that <hi>Offences</hi> are aggravated by the <hi>Greatneſs</hi> of the <hi>Offender;</hi> Riches and Greatneſs do not <hi>leſſen,</hi> but <hi>increaſe</hi> Mens Obligations to Duty; Theſe Bleſſings are a mighty truſt, with which men may do a great deal of good, and for which Almighty God will demand a ſeverer account than Ordinary. And ſuch Perſons ſhould conſider that their <hi>Examples</hi> are <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>conſpicuous,</hi> and have a great <hi>influence</hi> upon thoſe whom Providence has placed <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> them, and that therefore it becomes them to help to reform a <hi>Cuſtom</hi> ſo undeniably <hi>unlawful</hi> by giving a <hi>good</hi> Example, and by leading the way to others, without which 'twill hardly be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the fault of which will one day lye at <hi>their</hi> doors.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I do not well know what to call it, but another thing I have heard pretended, to put off this Duty, is to this Effect; All our Children hitherto have been baptized at home, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98039:14"/>had <hi>one</hi> baptized at Church. Let it be remembred, that I have already proved this to be a <hi>Duty,</hi> and then the force of this <hi>mighty</hi> Objection amounts to <hi>this;</hi> We have hitherto done amiſs all our Lives, and therefore we are reſolved to do ſo ſtill; We have never yet done our Duty, and therefore we never will. I will not expoſe the Folly of this pretence, it is enough to expoſe it ſelf.</p>
            <p>My Diſcourſe has hitherto been in <hi>General;</hi> But now I muſt apply myſelf more <hi>particularly</hi> to you of my own Charge. You ſee what the plain Laws of the Church are in this reſpect, and what ſtrong Obligations we <hi>all</hi> lye under to <hi>obey</hi> them; You ſee upon what great Strength of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Antiquity</hi> thoſe Laws of the Church are founded; Fathers and Councils, Abundance of the moſt eminent <hi>Divines,</hi> both <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Modern,</hi> giving their Teſtimonies to them; After all which, I cannot but hope, that you will readily comply, with what is here ſo plainly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be your Duty.</p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible of the great Tenderneſs both of <hi>Infants</hi> and of <hi>Parents,</hi> and therefore (tho I never yet heard of one Child that was injured by being brought to the Font) yet if your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be at any time really weak and in danger of Death, if by any accident whatever it ſo fall out, that they cannot ſafely be brought to <hi>Church,</hi> do not by any means ſuffer them to dye <hi>unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized;</hi> The Church in thoſe caſes of Sickneſs and extreme Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, has provided a Form of <hi>Private Baptiſm,</hi> and <hi>this</hi> you may be aſſured, I will always be ready to adminiſter; tho it were at <hi>Midnight.</hi> In this Office of <hi>Private Baptiſm,</hi> all that is <hi>Eſſential</hi> to the Sacrament is contained, and enough to ſecure the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Child, tho it ſhould die before the other Solemnities and Circumſtances be performed in the <hi>Church.</hi> And therefore when Perſons pretend a tender regard to the Weakneſs of the Child, to excuſe the bringing of it to the Church, and yet will not be contented to have it baptized at home, by the Form which is compoſed for that purpoſe, and <hi>ſufficient</hi> for the Childs Salvation; 'Tis evident, that <hi>ſomething elſe</hi> is at the <hi>Bottom,</hi> and that 'tis not ſo much their <hi>regard</hi> to the Safety and Welfare of the <hi>Infant,</hi> as the <hi>indulging</hi> of their own Humor, that is the cauſe of this <hi>Obſtinacy;</hi> for as for the <hi>Child,</hi> that is ſecured by the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,</hi> as well as by the <hi>Public</hi> Form. But if it live, and recover; then the<note n="*" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> Diſc. upon the whole Com. Prayer. <hi>p. 338.</hi> and the Rubrick for Private Baptiſm.</note> Rubrick adviſes that as ſoon as it is fit to be carried abroad, it be brought to the <hi>Church</hi> (not to be Baptized again, for that is done already) but that the <hi>Congregation</hi> may be certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Truth of the Baptiſm, before <hi>privately</hi> uſed, and that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98039:14"/>the <hi>Covenant</hi> may be <hi>ſolemnly</hi> entred into for it by the <hi>Sureties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And do not think that this ſhall put you to any <hi>double</hi> Charge or Trouble; for if in caſe of Neceſſity I come to your Houſes, to baptize any ſick Child, I expect no manner of Company, nor the leaſt Proviſion, nor any <hi>Reward</hi> from you; If you are Poor, I had rather you ſhould have ſomething from me.</p>
            <p>My readineſs to ſerve you in all other reſpects, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to come to the meaneſt of your Houſes in caſe of Sickneſs; My deſpiſing preſent Intereſt, and dealing <hi>impartially</hi> with all Perſons alike in this affair, cannot but convince you (if any thing will) that I am acted in it by pure <hi>Conviction,</hi> and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſolid Reaſon; Nor ſhould any thing elſe in the world have ever prevailed with me, to refuſe any of your Requeſts in this matter; I deſire you to excuſe me <hi>only</hi> from this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Cuſtom,</hi> and in any thing elſe, the Pooreſt of you may command my Attendance. If <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> (<hi>that is,</hi> a <hi>Diſcharge</hi> from complying with Laws) be thought <hi>reaſonable</hi> for <hi>others,</hi> all I deſire is a <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Obedience,</hi> a <hi>Liberty</hi> to <hi>obſerve,</hi> and <hi>obey</hi> thoſe Laws, to which I have <hi>ſubſcribed,</hi> and which ſtand <hi>unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed;</hi> and 'twill be very <hi>unreaſonable</hi> to deny me this.</p>
            <p>Whatever the Event be, I have <hi>now</hi> this ſatisfaction, that I have done all that in me lies, to reform a <hi>bad Cuſtom,</hi> which I thought to be my Duty; You ſee I have not refuſed it <hi>moroſely,</hi> without giving you any <hi>reaſon</hi> for ſo doing; but I have ventured that which is deareſt to me of any thing in the World, I mean my <hi>Reputation,</hi> to ſatisfy you, that this Practice ought to be amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I believe I have ſtudied this buſineſs <hi>more</hi> than you, and may <hi>modeſtly</hi> be allowed to underſtand it better; which is no more than I will readily grant to you, in your <hi>proper</hi> Callings and Imployments.</p>
            <p>I confeſs I ſhall never look upon my ſelf to be anſwered by an <hi>angry Reflection,</hi> or a <hi>diſdainful Smile;</hi> Scurrilous Railing and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling are things, which I have both <hi>Charity</hi> enough to <hi>forgive,</hi> and <hi>Magnanimity</hi> enough to <hi>deſpiſe.</hi> But if you can procure any one in the world to make a <hi>ſolid</hi> Anſwer to my Reaſons and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, I promiſe you I will readily retract my miſtakes, and ſhall be glad by that means to be put into a capacity of obliging you in <hi>this,</hi> as well as in <hi>other</hi> things; For I am ſo far from thinking it any <hi>real diſhonour,</hi> that I know 'tis a <hi>manly Generoſity,</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian Vertue,</hi> to change my opinion, upon the Evidence of better Reaſon; and that to perſiſt in an <hi>Error</hi> out of pure <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98039:15"/>and <hi>Stubbornneſs,</hi> does neither become the <hi>Ingenuity</hi> of a Man, nor the <hi>Religion</hi> of a Chriſtian; And therefore, if <hi>you</hi> find the Arguments of this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> are ſuch as cannot be <hi>fairly</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Let me beg and beſeech you then, as you love your own Souls, not <hi>wilfully</hi> and <hi>stubbornly</hi> to reſiſt the Truth. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that <hi>to him that knoweth to do good,</hi> in any inſtance of Duty, <hi>and yet doth it not, to him 'tis a Sin,</hi> in the higheſt Degree, <hi>Ja.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>I have now done with what I have to ſay of <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> But before I conclude, I cannot but take <hi>this Opportunity</hi> of leaving with you a brief Exhortation to the conſtant receiving of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lords Supper,</hi> a duty too much neglected amongſt you.</p>
            <p>Confider then I beſeech you, the Plainneſs, and the Poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Command, Do this in remembrance of me.</hi> And withal remember that the <hi>Only way to enter into Life, is to keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> in general, <hi>this</hi> as well as the <hi>reſt;</hi> and that Chriſt will one day <hi>execute his Vengeance, on all that obey not the Laws of his Goſpel,</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.8. of which this is <hi>one,</hi> and of the <hi>higheſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> too.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider that is the Command of Chriſt your Soveraign Lord, who as your King and Supream Governor, has an <hi>abſolute</hi> right, and a juſt Claim to your <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Obedience, nor can you deny it in any inſtance whatever, without the higheſt Injuſtice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider further, that 'tis the dying Command of <hi>Jeſus</hi> your Saviour and Redeemer, your <hi>greateſt Friend,</hi> and your <hi>best Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor;</hi> who ſtopt at no <hi>Dangers,</hi> nor declined any <hi>Sufferings</hi> to do you ſervice; who freely parted with his own deareſt and invalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able blood, to ranſom, and redeem your Souls; to purchaſe for you the pardon of your Sins, the Graces of Gods Spirit, and the immortal Joys of Heaven. Who was contented to undergo all the Malice of Men and Devils, <hi>to be a man of ſorrows and acquainted with grief</hi> through the whole Scene of his Life; to endure the greateſt Torments of Body, and Agonies of Mind; to ſweat and groan, to bleed and die, to deliver you from Eternal Death. 'Tis <hi>this Jeſus</hi> that commands you, to <hi>do this in remembrance of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that here is both the higheſt <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>command,</hi> and the greateſt <hi>Love</hi> in the world to <hi>invite</hi> your Obedience. Will you then diſobey a <hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>Saviour</hi> too, a <hi>Soveraign Lord,</hi> and a <hi>Merciful Redeemer</hi> at once? Alas! What unpardonable <hi>Rebellion,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98039:15"/>What ſcandalous <hi>Ingratitude</hi> is this? Bleſſed Jeſu! What return can be ſufficient, What thanks can be big enough for ſuch ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Love? And yet it is no hard or difficult, but a very eaſy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quital, that the Son of God expects from us, 'tis only that we fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently remember his dying Love, in that <hi>Memorial Feaſt,</hi> he has appointed for that purpoſe; that we there thankfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate his Mercy, ſolemnly renew and ratify our Baptiſmal Vows and Engagements, and enter into a ſacred League of Peace, and Love and Charity with all the world. A poor return, God knows, this is, for ſo great a Mercy, and ſhall we yet refuſe to pay <hi>this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider that you are bound in <hi>Intereſt,</hi> as well as in duty, to pay a conſtant Attendance on this ſacred <hi>Ordinance.</hi> For 'tis the moſt likely means in the world to make all your Prayers ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful at the Throne of Grace, and to fetch down even <hi>temporal</hi> Bleſſings upon you; And 'tis the moſt probable means in the world to promote and advance your <hi>everlaſting</hi> well-being; to confirm and increaſe your <hi>Faith,</hi> to heighten your <hi>Repentance,</hi> to raiſe your <hi>Sorrow</hi> for Sin, and your Hatred againſt it; To inflame your <hi>Love,</hi> your <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> to God, and your crucified Saviour, and your <hi>Charity</hi> to all your Fellow creatures; 'tis the beſt way to advance your <hi>Hope,</hi> to improve all your Graces, to make all your Sins give up the Ghoſt, and yield themſelves per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Victims to a Redeemers conquering Love. In ſhort, the bleſſed Sacrament, to every devout and worthy Receiver is full of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and heavenly Bleſſings; 'tis not only our <hi>greateſt Duty,</hi> but 'tis our <hi>higheſt Priviledge</hi> too.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Reaſons,</hi> what <hi>Pretences</hi> then can be ſtrong enough to keep you from ſo ſacred and <hi>advantageous</hi> a Duty? You know what I have formerly ſaid at large to remove them all; There are two faults, that you may be guilty of in this affair; Either by a careleſs <hi>refuſal</hi> and <hi>neglect</hi> of this <hi>bleſſed Sacrament,</hi> or by an unworthy <hi>abuſe</hi> and <hi>profanation</hi> of it; by <hi>unworthily</hi> coming to it, or by <hi>profanely</hi> turning your backs upon it; Both theſe are Sins <hi>equally</hi> dangerous, and I beſeech you by all the Hopes of Heaven, and Fears of Hell to avoid both. I have formerly and often told you how this may be done; But if there be any Soul amongſt you that wants either farther <hi>Inſtruction,</hi> or <hi>Satisfaction</hi> in this matter, I once more earneſtly deſire and invite all ſuch to come to me for my private help and direction; Come freely and without ſcruple, the Pooreſt, the Meaneſt of you; By the Bleſſing of God, you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98039:16"/>ſhall not go away without the beſt Aſſiſtance and Incouragement I am able to givé you.</p>
            <p>And in order to the fitting your ſelves for the <hi>Bleſſed Sacrament</hi> I muſt beg and entreat you to lead pious and ſober, juſt and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Lives. <hi>Impenitence</hi> and an obſtinate going on in Sin, is the only thing, that makes men unworthy of the Sacrament; A good man, a true ſincere penitent, who underſtands competently the Nature of the Sacrament, and is heartily reſolved to forſake all his paſt Sins, and to lead a new Life, ſuch a one is fit to come to the <hi>Sacrament</hi> at any time; And he who will not do this, is not fit to die, nor can he go to Heaven.</p>
            <p>And to enable you to lead this pious Chriſtian Life, let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you often and daily upon your bended Knees, to petition Almighty God, for his <hi>preventing, aſſiſting,</hi> and <hi>ſupporting</hi> Grace. Morning and Evening at leaſt, let me deſire every Soul amongſt you to ſpend ſome little time in that divine and heavenly, that honorable, and advantageous duty of Prayer. You that have Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies muſt pray with them; and teach your Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to live in the Fear of God; Inſtruct and <hi>Catechize</hi> them in the Principles of Religion as well as you are able, and ſend them to the <hi>Church,</hi> to be inſtructed better; As they grow up, you muſt warn them often of the baſeneſs and danger of Sin in general; of <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Curſing,</hi> of <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> and <hi>profaning the Lords day,</hi> Vices to which Youth are <hi>extreamly</hi> addicted. Tell them of the Excellency of a pious, ſober, righteous Life, and of the glorious rewards that attend it; teach them by your <hi>Example,</hi> as well as by your <hi>Inſtructions;</hi> You will have the <hi>Comfort</hi> of it in this Life, and be <hi>rewarded</hi> for it in a better.</p>
            <p>From the Prayers of the Church, I would deſire you never to be <hi>wilfully</hi> abſent; Come at the beginning, and behave your ſelves devoutly at them; And for your <hi>Private</hi> Devotion, I have here compoſed a ſhort Form, which I deſire all ſuch of you, as have not better helps at hand, to ſay daily, <hi>humbly</hi> and <hi>devoutly</hi> upon your Knees.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <p>
                  <hi>O God the Father of Heaven, have mercy upon me a miſerable Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner! O thou God of Angels and men, the Creator and Preſerver of all the world, I have ſinned, I have ſinned againſt Heaven and againſt thee, I have been a ſtubborn and a rebellious Child, but do not thou, O Lord caſt off the bowels and compaſſions of a Father. I have perverted all the ends of my Creation, I have deſpiſed thy Authority, abuſed thy Mercy, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98039:16"/>provoked thy Vengeance; But O thou, who willeſt not the Death of a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, have Mercy upon me! For thy Names ſake pardon mine Iniquities for they are great; for thine own Mercies ſake, for thy dear Son, and my Saviours ſake, have pity upon me a miſerable Sinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O bleſſed Jeſus, the High-Prieſt, the Saviour and Redeemer of Souls, have Mercy upon me! Let thy Stripes and Wounds, thy Croſs and Paſſion, plead and intercede for me; By thine Agony and bloody Sweat, by all that thou didſt and ſufferedst for Sinners, ſave and deliver me, in the hour of Death, and the day of Judgment; And ſuffer not, O holy Redeemer, my Soul, which is the purchaſe of thine own meritorious blood, to periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O holy Spirit of Grace, the Sanctifier of all the Elect People of God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, I beſeech thee, into my Soul the Principles of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Piety; Sanctify me throughout, in Body and Mind, in Heart, Will, and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; I am undone if thou leave me to my ſelf, follow me by thy moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and awaken my Conſcience by thy bleſſed Suggeſtions, or I periſh for ever. Quicken and excite my languiſhing Vertues; Allure my hope by the glorious rewards of Obedience; Alarm my fear by the ſtedfaſt belief of a judgment to come; Affect my gratitude and love, by a deep ſence of the amazing mercies of my God and Saviour; and by all let me be led to a ſpeedy and vigorous Repentance, to ſuch a pious and godly, ſober and humble, juſt and charitable life, us becomes a Diſciple of the moſt holy Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, three perſons, and one God! O holy and undivided Trinity, have mercy upon me a miſerable ſinner!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Glory be to thee, O God, for all the mercies I have received; Take me into thy Protection [this day] or [this night] and all that belong to me; Bleſs all my Civil, Spiritual, and Natural Parents, Relations and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors; Reward all my Friends and Benefactors; Forgive and turn the hearts of my worſt and greateſt Enemies; Let thy Goſpel, and Truth, thy Peace and Salvation extend it ſelf to all the World; for the ſake of Jeſus my Saviour; In whoſe Name and Words, I further pray. Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="canon_law">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98039:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Canon</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>ALL Miniſters ſhall obſerve the <hi>Orders,</hi> Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies preſcribed in the Book of Common Prayer,— without either <hi>diminiſhing,</hi> or adding any thing in the Matter or Form thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Canon</hi> 38.</p>
               <p>If any Miniſter after Subſcription, ſhall omit to uſe the Form of Prayer, or <hi>any of the Orders</hi> or Ceremonies preſcribed in the Communion-Book, Let him be ſuſpended: And if after a month be do not reform and ſubmit himſelf, Let him be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated: And then if he ſhall not ſubmit himſelf within the ſpace of another month, Let him be depoſed from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Canon</hi> 81.</p>
               <p>There ſhall be a Font of Stone in every Church and Chapel where Baptiſm is to be adminiſtred. — <hi>In which only Font</hi> the Miniſter ſhall Baptize <hi>Publickly:</hi> that is, no doubt, <hi>with the Form of Publick Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
